Guide to the Downtown Brooklyn Development Association records 1979.021
Brooklyn Historical Society
Downtown Brooklyn Development Association records
1929 to circa 1985
1979.021
Brooklyn Historical Society
4.75 linear feet in nine manuscript boxes and one oversize folder
This collection comprises the subject files of the Downtown Brooklyn Development Association. The association was founded in 1929 as a civic group concerned with the problems of the business and shopping center in downtown Brooklyn. The papers are news clippings, correspondence, brochures, newsletters, pamphlets, legislative documents, photographs, city plans and maps, and other items relating to organizations and causes with which the association was involved. The majority of the documents were produced by external bodies or individuals but were integral the association's activities. The three subjects most comprehensively addressed are the development of the Brooklyn Civic Center (Cadman Plaza), the redevelopment of Fulton Street, and traffic and transportation.
Downtown Brooklyn Development Association.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by subject.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction. Many of the news clippings are fragile, please handle them with care.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
These records were collected by the Downtown Brooklyn Development Association (DBDA) and maintained as their subject files until the Long Island Historical Society (LIHS) received them in October, 1975. One additional oversize folder of material was donated to the LIHS by the DBDA, circa 1985.
Historical Note
The Downtown Brooklyn Development Association was founded in 1929 as a civic group concerned with the problems of the business and shopping center in downtown Brooklyn. Their slogan was “In the interest of a better downtown Brooklyn.” The association closely monitored legislative activities which would assist or hinder the businesses in the area and organized support or opposition where necessary. They focused on attracting business owners and shoppers to Brooklyn through improved traffic and transit, redevelopment of the governmental buildings at Cadman Plaza, and beautification projects. The directors and officers of the association were comprised of prominent local business owners and presidents, vice-presidents, and chairmen of businesses including The Dime Savings Bank of Brooklyn, Abraham & Straus, Inc., the Brooklyn Eagle, Pyle-Gray Real Estate Co., the Brooklyn-Manhattan Transit Corp., the Brooklyn Union Gas Company, the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn, and the New York Telephone Company.
Scope and Contents
This collection comprises the subject files of the Downtown Brooklyn Development Association. The papers are news clippings, correspondence, brochures, newsletters, pamphlets, legislative documents, photographs, city plans and maps, and other items relating to organizations and causes with which the association was involved or which the association sponsored. The majority of the documents were produced by external bodies or individuals but were integral the association's activities. The only materials produced by the members of the association are copies of correspondence. The three subjects most comprehensively addressed are the development of the Brooklyn Civic Center (Cadman Plaza), the redevelopment of Fulton Street, and traffic and transportation.
With regard to the Civic Center, the documents cover the renovation and construction of Borough Hall and the court houses as well as other buildings and facilities in the area such as the Red Cross building, Brooklyn Law School, the public library, and parking structures. The papers discussing the redevelopment of Fulton Street primarily address the removal of the elevated train and the development of the area as a downtown Brooklyn shopping district. The papers regarding traffic and transportation issues are tied in with Robert Moses. He was influential in the development of the Brooklyn Battery Tunnel, the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway, and the Verazano Narrows Bridge, all of which were concerns of the Downtown Brooklyn Development Association. There are also papers which address the three lines of the subway system: the Independent Subway System, the Interborough Rapid Transit Company, and the Brooklyn Manhattan Transit Corporation.
Although the main interest of the association was the Brooklyn Heights area, they were also concerned with other areas of Brooklyn. This is predominately shown in the traffic files, but there are also papers concerning the redesign of the Pratt Institute Campus in Fort Green and information throughout multiple files on Prospect Park and the neighborhood of Park Slope. The only folder which is designated solely to the administrative concerns of the association is the Resignations folder. This contains correspondence from member businesses declining to continue their membership.
Abraham & Straus.; American Red Cross.; Better Business Bureau of New York City.; Blum, Robert E.; Bourke-White, Margaret, 1904-1971; Brooklyn Borough Hall (New York, N.Y.).; Brooklyn Chamber of Commerce (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Brooklyn daily eagle.; Brooklyn Law School.; Brooklyn Public Library.; Brooklyn-Manhattan Transit Company.; Citizens Budget Commission (New York, N.Y.).; Citizens Union Foundation (New York, N.Y.).; Citizens' Zoning Committee, Inc..; Davenport, Henry J.; Downtown Brooklyn Development Association.; Ebbets Field (New York, N.Y.).; Independent Subway System (New York, N.Y.).; Interborough Rapid Transit Company.; Moses, Robert, 1888-1981; New York (N.Y.). City Planning Commission.; New York (N.Y.). Dept. of Commerce and Industrial Development.; New York (N.Y.). Dept. of Correction.; New York (N.Y.). Dept. of Parks.; New York (N.Y.). Dept. of Public Works.; New York (N.Y.). Dept. of Traffic.; New York (N.Y.). Landmarks Preservation Commission.; New York Naval Shipyard.; Pratt Institute.; Regional Plan Association (New York, N.Y.).; Roscoe, Andrew S.; Stamm, Godfrey A.; Swift, Thomas A.; Triborough Bridge and Tunnel Authority.; Blueprints (reprographic copies); Brochures; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn-Battery Tunnel (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn-Queens Expressway (New York, N.Y.); Central business districts; City planning; Clippings (information artifacts); Community centers |z New York (State) |z New York; Correspondence; Courthouses |z New York (State) |z New York; George Washington Bridge (New York, N.Y.); Holland Tunnel (New York, N.Y.); Legislative hearings; Lincoln Tunnel (New York, N.Y.); Local transit |z New York (State) |z New York; Maps; Negatives (photographic); Newsletters; Pamphlets; Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Parks |z New York (State) |z New York; Photographs; Post office buildings |z New York (State) |z New York; Press releases; Prospect Park (New York, N.Y.); Railroads, Elevated; Resolutions (administrative records); Speeches; Throgs Neck Bridge (New York, N.Y.); Transportation; Urban renewal |z New York (State) |z New York; Verrazano-Narrows Bridge (New York, N.Y.)
- Abraham and Straus Garage, 1958-1959 (Box 1 of 9)
- American Red Cross, 1949-1957 (Box 1 of 9)
- Annual window dispaly competition, Bulk, 1935-1936; 1929-1936 (Box 1 of 9)
- Anti-crime committee, 1951-1952 (Box 1 of 9)
- Architectural competition, 1941 (Box 1 of 9)
- Auction sales, 1950-1958 (Box 1 of 9)
- Better Business Bureau, 1946-1957 (Box 1 of 9)
- Better Government in New York, 1952-1956 (Box 1 of 9)
- Borough Hall, 1948-1963 (Box 1 of 9)
- Brooklyn Airlines Terminal, 1946-1950 (Box 1 of 9)
- Brooklyn Baseball Club, 1957 (Box 1 of 9)
- Brooklyn Battery Tunnel, 1938-1940 (Box 1 of 9)
- Brooklyn Battery Tunnel, 1950-1951 (Box 1 of 9)
- Brooklyn Battery Tunnel Plan Photographs, no date (Box 1 of 9)
- Brooklyn Bridge Plaza, Bulk, 1935; 1931-1941 (Box 1 of 9)
- Brooklyn Bridge Plaza Plan Photograph, no date (Box 1 of 9)
- Brooklyn Bridge Reopening, 1954 (Box 2 of 9)
- Brooklyn Civic Center, 1952-1955 (Box 2 of 9)
- Brooklyn Civic Center, 1954-1955 (Box 2 of 9)
- Brooklyn Civic Center, Brochure, 1952-1955 (Box 2 of 9)
- Brooklyn Heliport, 1954-1961 (Box 2 of 9)
- Brooklyn Navy Yard, 1963-1966 (Box 2 of 9)
- Brooklyn Navy Yard, 1966-1970 (Box 2 of 9)
- Brooklyn Public Library, 1941-1956 (Box 3 of 9)
- Brooklyn-Queens Expressway, Bulk, 1956-1968; 1943-1968 (Box 3 of 9)
- Brooklyn War Memorial, 1945-1951 (Box 3 of 9)
- Buses, 1934-1942 (Box 3 of 9)
- Carpenter, J. Henry, 1949-1954 (Box 3 of 9)
- Census, Federal (New York City), 1955 (Box 3 of 9)
- Citizens Budget Commission, 1948-1957 (Box 3 of 9)
- Citizens Conference on City Planning, 1942-1952 (Box 3 of 9)
- Citizens Union, 1951-1953 (Box 3 of 9)
- Citizens Zoning Committee, 1942-1953 (Box 3 of 9)
- City Planning Commission, 1940-1959 (Box 4 of 9)
- Committee on Planning and Zoning, 1941-1943 (Box 4 of 9)
- Community College, 1952-1955 (Box 4 of 9)
- Concord Village, 1949-1955 (Box 4 of 9)
- Cross Brooklyn Expressway, 1965-1969 (Box 4 of 9)
- Department of Air pollution and control, 1957 (Box 4 of 9)
- Detention, Brooklyn House of, 1956-1957 (Box 4 of 9)
- Directomat, 1956, no date (Box 4 of 9)
- Domestic Relations Court (Brooklyn), April 4, 1956 (Box 4 of 9)
- Education, Board of, 1956 (Box 4 of 9)
- Estimate, Board of, November 14, 1956 (Box 4 of 9)
- Facts about Brooklyn- Family Income Data, 1950-1958 (Box 4 of 9)
- Facts about Brooklyn- Family Income Data, 1957-1966 (Box 4 of 9)
- Federal Building, 1951-1952 (Box 5 of 9)
- Five counties, 1952-1957 (Box 5 of 9)
- Fluoridation- Information materials, 1950-1957 (Box 5 of 9)
- Forsythia Day, 1940-1952 (Box 5 of 9)
- Freedom Train in Brooklyn, 1947-1949 (Box 5 of 9)
- Fulton Street Closing, 1957-1959 (Box 5 of 9)
- Fulton Street elevated, 1929-1938 (Box 5 of 9)
- Fulton Street elevated, 1937-1939 (Box 5 of 9)
- Fulton Street elevated, 1940-1941 (Box 5 of 9)
- Fulton Street elevated, 1941-1943 (Box 5 of 9)
- Fulton Street "EL" Removal Assessments, 1941-1943 (Box 5 of 9)
- Fulton Street "EL" Removal Celebration, 1941 (Box 6 of 9)
- Fulton Street "EL" Removal Clippings, Bulk, 1940; 1929-1943 (Box 6 of 9)
- Fulton Street "EL" Removal Fund, 1937-1939 (Box 6 of 9)
- Fulton Street "EL" Removal- Mayor's Committee on Removal of EL. Structures in NYC, 1935-1937 (Box 6 of 9)
- Fulton Street Exhibit, 1940-1941 (Box 6 of 9)
- Housing (New), Brooklyn Civic Center, 1944-1955 (Box 6 of 9)
- Kingsview, 1952-1955 (Box 6 of 9)
- Long Island Railroad, 1952-1955 (Box 6 of 9)
- Long Island Railroad Photographs, March 15, 1954 (Box 6 of 9)
- Manhattan Bridge, 1959-1960 (Box 6 of 9)
- Miscellaneous: Historic Preservation and Landmarks, Bulk, 1961-1970; 1941-1970 (Box 7 of 9)
- Miscellaneous: History, Bulk, 1954-1966; 1944-1971 (Box 7 of 9)
- Miscellaneous: Redevelopment, Bulk, 1954-1970; 1944-1970 (Box 7 of 9)
- Montague Street Library, 1951-1954 (Box 7 of 9)
- Moses, Robert, Parks Commissioner, 1951-1954 (Box 7 of 9)
- Myrtle Avenue "EL" Demolition, 1965-1970 (Box 7 of 9)
- Myrtle Avenue Garage, 1952-1955 (Box 7 of 9)
- Narrows Bridge (Gowanus Expressway), 1954-1961 (Box 7 of 9)
- Narrows Bridge (Gowanus Expressway) Photographs and Plan Photographs, no date (Box 7 of 9)
- Pratt Institute, 1952 (Box 7 of 9)
- Prospect Park Centennial, 1965-1966 (Box 8 of 9)
- Raymond Street Jail Closing, 1958-1967 (Box 8 of 9)
- Red Cross, Bulk, 1952; 1945-1952 (Box 8 of 9)
- Redevelopment, Boerum Place Widening, 1957-1962 (Box 8 of 9)
- Redevelopment, Federal Court House and Office Building, 1956-1964 (Box 8 of 9)
- Redevelopment, Supreme Court Building (New), 1957-1959 (Box 8 of 9)
- Redevelopment, Supreme Court Building (Old Site), Brooklyn Law School, 1960-1965 (Box 8 of 9)
- Redevelopment, 215 Montague Street, Bulk, 1957-1959; 1947-1959 (Box 8 of 9)
- Resignations, 1929-1944 (Box 8 of 9)
- Sales Tax Exemption, 1956 (Box 8 of 9)
- Sidewalks, 1929-1942 (Box 8 of 9)
- Sports Authority, Dodgers Stadium, 1956-1957 (Box 9 of 9)
- Squibb & Sons, 1956-1957 (Box 9 of 9)
- Staples-Smith, 1956, no date (Box 9 of 9)
- Street Directories for Police Squad, no date (Box 9 of 9)
- Subway Stations, Sub-Committee of Redevelopment Committee, 1956 (Box 9 of 9)
- Subway Strike, 1957 (Box 9 of 9)
- Traffic and Transit Committee, 1947-1952 (Box 9 of 9)
- Traffic and Transit Committee, 1947-1952 (Box 9 of 9)
- Traffic and Transit Committee, 1953-1954 (Box 9 of 9)
- Traffic and Transit Photographic Record of Pierpont and Clinton Streets, 1947 (Box 9 of 9)
- Verrazano Narrows Bridge, 1962-1969 (Box 9 of 9)
- York College, 1967 (Box 9 of 9)
- Oversize material, 1969 - circa 1985 (Box OS-22)
  General note
  Contains Brownstoned in Brooklyn 2 pamphlet, Cinderella II pamphlet, Downtown Brooklyn walking tour memo, Wall Street +5 / 111 Livingston Street brochure, and clippings